{
    "tossups": [
        {
            "question": "Adolf Jann was the founding president of a Swiss organization that supported these entities and the policy behind them. One of these entities was created for the Baster people around the town of Rehoboth. Four of these places, the TBVC, were given additional autonomy compared to the others. For their performance within one of these places at the Sun City resort, the band Queen was blacklisted, and these places earned much of their revenue from casinos and strip clubs. These places were the brainchild of (*) Hendrik Verwoerd and were subjected to a plan of \u201cseparate development\u201d from the white and colored areas of the country. For 10 points, identify these \u201chomelands\u201d created for South African blacks during apartheid.",
            "answer": "bantustans (accept Bantu homeland, black homeland, black state, or homeland)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Alexandre de Rhodes was one of the first Europeans to visit this city and created a Romanization system for the local language. A massive bronze drum from the \u0110\u00f4ng S\u01a1n culture filled with plow shares, hoes, and weapons was found in the 1980\u2019s near this modern city at the site of Co Loa. Fran\u00e7ois Garnier died while leading an 18-man charge out of this city while defending it from an attack headed by the Black Flag Army. This capital of the L\u00fd (\u201clee\u201d) (*) Dynasty was returned to its original name meaning \u201cSoaring Dragon\u201d in 1802 after it lost capital status to Hu\u1ebf. This city was liberated from its 20 year domination by the Ming under L\u00ea L\u1ee3i and John McCain spent some of his time as a POW in this city\u2019s \u201cHilton\u201d. For 10 points, name this capital of Vietnam.",
            "answer": "Hanoi",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Among others, Adrienne Clarkson, a former holder of this office, has proposed that the selection process for this post include a televised trivia quiz on the country it represents. Another person in this position claimed that the conflict between the conservative culture of the Patriotes and that of the majority had created a rebellion. In 1952, Vincent Massey became the first holder of this position to not be a member of the (*) peerage. Perhaps the best known holder of this office did not dissolve Parliament at the request of Prime Minister William Lyon Mackenzie King. For 10 points, this is what position held by the likes of John Lambton, 1st Earl of Durham and Julian Byng that represents the monarch of the Commonwealth in America\u2019s northern neighbor?",
            "answer": "Governour General of Canada",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "One minister of a ruler targeted by this declaration said that, \u201cMy master's sword is steel; the Pope's is made of words\" in response to its issuance. The pope who promulgated this bull was mocked in the forged document Deum Time and that pope was later captured and beaten in part because of this declaration. The trial of Bernard Saisset contributed to the issuance of this bull. This declaration was preceded by the bull Etsi de statu, which reversed a previous bull issued only a year and a half prior regarding (*) taxing the clergy. That bull was Clericis laicos. This declaration states that the sword of spiritual authority is superior to the one of temporal authority. For 10 points, what is this bull issued by Boniface VIII in an attempt to assert papal authority over the kings of Europe?",
            "answer": "Unam Sanctam",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "This ruler\u2019s homosocial relationship with the Georgian slave Malik Ayaz inspired numerous songs and poems by later authors and led to Ayaz being installed as the king of a conquered city. This leader rose to power after defeating his brother Ismail in a battle named for his future capital and confined that brother to a castle in Joorjan. The author of the most famous literary work produced under this king\u2019s patronage was supposedly cheated of most of his payment by a spiteful courtier who switched the gold this ruler had allocated for the author with silver. This ruler\u2019s defeat of Khalaf ibn Ahmad ended the Saffarid Dynasty. This leader sacked the (*) Somnath Temple, destroying its jyotirlinga and using the gold from it for a mosque in his capital. This ruler was the first to use the title \u201csultan\u201d and is best known for his 17 campaigns east of the Khyber Pass. For 10 points, identify this patron of Ferdowsi and habitual raider of northern India, the most powerful ruler of the Ghaznavid Dynasty.",
            "answer": "Mahmud of Ghazni or Yam\u012bn-ud-Dawla Abul-Q\u0101\u1e63im Ma\u1e25m\u016bd ibn Seb\u00fckteg\u012bn",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "This quote titles one of Guy Patterson\u2019s drum solos in the 1996 movie That Thing You Do!. The fines levied against Paul Chambers for jokingly threatening to blow up an airport on Twitter in 2010 led to thousands of tweets supporting him using this quote as their hashtag. For crowd scenes in its original source, this quote was recorded at a Michigan State-Notre Dame football game. In Monty Python\u2019s Life of Brian, this quote is parodied by a man on a cross who uses it to escape punishment while another man claims that it applies to him and his (*) wife. This quote is originally the response to a Roman officer\u2019s request to a defeated army to identify the leader of a slave rebellion. For 10 points, what is this quote from a 1960 movie in which an army of Roman slaves claims to be the namesake person?",
            "answer": "\u201cI am Spartacus!\u201d or \u201cI\u2019m Spartacus!\u201d",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "One person in this profession took the name Nicholas Gaspard upon converting to Catholicism and founded the Shibazhi organization. A man in this profession adorned his clothes with bells and feuded with Ling Tong after joining the military. The Ningbo Massacre was carried out by people of this profession against Portuguese people in this profession. Ching Shih took over a successful operation in this business after the death of her husband and had an affair with her stepson (*) Cheung Po Tsai. The first profession of Gan Ning, the Joseon Kingdom launched the Gihae Eastern Expedition against people in this profession based on Tsushima Island and those people most actively raided the southeast coast of China during the Ming Dynasty. For 10 points, this is what profession, most famously held in East Asia by the Wokou?",
            "answer": "piracy (accept equivalents/word forms)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "One loss by this general led to some of his men being held in the Exchange and Provost \u201cDungeon\u201d and he was later exchanged for William Philips. This man would later successfully disperse a rebel army after marching 30 miles through a snowstorm. This man\u2019s highest post was supplanted by a similarly named position whose first holder was Henry Knox. Though this general commanded the right flank, the Hudson River (*) separated his normal forces from the fighting during the Battle of Saratoga. Due to the city\u2019s inadequate defenses, this general surrendered Charleston to Henry Clinton. For 10 points, name this Continental general perhaps best known for his victory at Petersham during Shay\u2019s Rebellion and accepting the British surrender at Yorktown.",
            "answer": "Benjamin Lincoln",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Plutarch writes that Damoteles was a commander in this institution at the Battle of Sellasia, suggesting it may have served reconnaissance purposes. Brandon Ross claims that this institution evolved as an adaptation to warfare in mountainous terrain, and it may have served as training for the hippeis. A traditional historiographical debate over the role of this institution claims that it was either a means of (*) policing the state or just an extension of the ag\u014dg\u0113. This institution was legitimized by a yearly declaration of war by the ephors and specifically targeted the strongest men in order to mitigate the risks of a slave rebellion. For 10 points, name this institution primarily known for young Spartan men covertly murdering helots.",
            "answer": "krypteia",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "This ruler had his mother Sadij\u00e9 (\u201csah-dee-yay\u201d) supervise the royal kitchen because he feared being poisoned. This man purchased the massive Knollwood Manor in New York, but never occupied it. This ruler survived an assassination attempt while at a performance of Pagliacci in Vienna, leading to the expulsion from the city of all political emigres from his country. This man\u2019s namesake salute consists of placing one\u2019s right hand over the heart with the palm facing down. This leader nationalized all Catholic schools in his country and slashed the national budget in an attempt to shake off (*) Italian economic domination. Claiming to be the many times great-grand-nephew of Skanderbeg, for 10 points, name this most recent king of Albania deposed by Mussolini\u2019s Italy.",
            "answer": "King Zog I of Albania (or Ahmet Muhtar Zogolli)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Husain ibn Sulaiman constructed a palace now called Husuni Kubwa in a city in this cultural region that was largely built with coral. The Abushiri Revolt took place in this cultural region and was suppressed by English and German forces. One city in this cultural region was attacked by the Zimba cannibals, prompting Portugal to take control of the city in 1589, and is also home to the Twelve Nations who preserve the culture of the city\u2019s original inhabitants. The city of Sofala in this cultural region was once believed to be the Biblical cities of either Ophir or Tarshish. (*) Zheng He\u2019s \u201cqilin\u201d (\u201cchee-lean\u201d) came from the city of Malindi in this cultural region. Home to trading cities like Kilwa, Mombasa, and Zanzibar, for 10 points, name this cultural region of East Africa on the Indian Ocean named for the lingua franca of Kenya and Tanzania.",
            "answer": "Swahili Coast (prompt on descriptive [e.g. \u201cthe coast of East Africa\u201d] or more specific answers, such as any city mentioned in the question)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "One of these places in Colombia was called \u201cEl Infiernito\u201d, or \u201cLittle Hell\u201d, by conquistadors for its association with paganism. Jesuit Ferdinand Verbiest was placed in charge of one of these places after winning a contest against Yang Guangxian. In the Muslim world, these places created z\u012bj, a famous example of which was produced from one of these places in Maragheh, Azerbaijan. Five of these places known as Jantar Mantar were built by the (*) Rajput ruler Jai Singh II and the one in Jaipur contains the Vrihat Samrat Yantra, the \u201cgreat king of instruments\u201d. One of these places built by Ulugh Beg in Samarkand accurately measured the Earth\u2019s tilt and the length of the solar year. For 10 points, identify these places used for the study of celestial bodies.",
            "answer": "observatories",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A cartoon in Harper\u2019s Magazine depicted one of the proponents of this act as a triumphant Roman general in a chariot labelled \u201cSugar Trust\u201d. That cartoon also shows the president pulled behind the chariot and that president called this act \u201cparty perfidy and party dishonor\u201d. One of the namesakes of this bill was instrumental in adding over 600 amendments to it while it was in the Senate, making it increasingly (*) protectionist. A notable part of this legislation targeted the rich and affected less than 10% of Americans. For 10 points, name this 1894 act that lowered tariffs from the McKinley Tariff and created a 2% income tax, the first in American peacetime.",
            "answer": "Wilson-Gorman Tariff Act (accept names in either order)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A European visitor in this man\u2019s court once said of his wife that \u201c[she] perhaps in another milieu would have been a Christina of Sweden or a Catherine the Great.\u201d This ruler approached the predecessor in his most famous position with a rock on his neck in a traditional gesture of submission and that predecessor recognized him as the leader of Shewa. This ruler supposedly ordered three electric (*) chairs for his kingdom, but had no means of producing electricity, and so used one as a throne. This man succeeded Yohannes IV despite not being the chosen successor by claiming that he could trace a direct male ancestry to King Solomon. This husband of Taytu Betul was supported by England, France, and Russia in a war sparked by a translation discrepancy in the Treaty of Wuchale. For 10 points, who was this Emperor of Ethiopia who defeated Italy at the Battle of Adwa?",
            "answer": "Menelik II (accept Sahle Maryam)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "During the minority of one member of this family, a regency called the Turtici passed a law forbidding anyone in their domain from acquiring an education outside their area of rule. One member of this family had a coat of arms with a rhino based on D\u00fcrer\u2019s woodcut, and his successor, of a junior branch of this family, rose to power with the help of supporters called Palleschi. One member of this family was rewarded for his support of the papacy with alum mines, bringing him substantial wealth, and his son was called (*) Pater Patriae. Raphael painted two members of this family who were high-ranking members of the clergy. One member of this family was killed and another was injured in 1478 while attending High Mass at the Duomo due to an assassination attempt by the Pazzi family. For 10 points, name this Florentine family including Cosimo and Lorenzo the Magnificent.",
            "answer": "Medici family",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Complications of this behavior relating to birth have been partially addressed by the increased altriciality of human infants compared to other primates. Concealed ovulation and modest male canine size support the \u201cprovisioning\u201d model for the origin of this behavior. The oldest known evidence for this behavior in Europe was found at Happisburgh in 2013. This behavior led to the placement of the foramen magnum at the base of the skull. Because of their stocky frames and wide (*) pelvises, Neanderthals required more energy to do this relative to modern humans, making them less efficient at pursuing prey. Raising the head above savanna grasses and freeing the hands are two results, and perhaps causes, for the development of this behavior. For 10 points, identify this behavior in which humans use only two limbs for locomotion.",
            "answer": "human bipedalism (accept logical equivalents, e.g. walking on two legs; prompt on just  walking)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "After conquering his future capital, the first ruler of this empire used the Badshahi Mosque as a stable and its minarets were later used as a gun tower to attack the Alamgiri Gate of a nearby fort. This empire\u2019s most elite military division was the Fauj-i-Khas, which was trained in French in European tactics by officers like Jean-Baptiste Ventura and Jean-Fran\u00e7ois Allard. Victories at the battles of Attock and Jamrud, among others, brought this empire to its westernmost extent at the expense of the (*) Durrani Empire. This empire fell after the Battle of Gujrat to the British, the last South Asian state to do so, and was founded after the conquest of Lahore by Ranjit Singh. For 10 points, name this empire that developed from the Dal Khalsa and ruled the Punjab from 1799-1849.",
            "answer": "Sikh Empire",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "ANSWER: Sikh Empire  18. James Hall piloted three expeditions to this place in the 17th century to find silver and the mythical Buss Island. The travels of the Portuguese brothers Gaspar and Miguel Cortes-Real led to the accurate depiction of the south coast of this place on the Cantino planisphere. While exploring this place, Peter Freuchen was buried in a blizzard and had to dig his way out with a pick made of his own crap, and upon returning to his camp, amputated his toes with a pair of pliers. Bartering between people of this place and Scottish whalers was called troaking. In the 1930\u2019s, (*) Norway claimed this place was terra nullius and attempted to create a settlement named after this place\u2019s discoverer. Hans Egede founded a mission in this place near what would become the city of Godthab. For 10 points, name this North Atlantic island that appears larger than Africa on Mercator projections.",
            "answer": "Greenland (or Kalaallit Nunaat)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Most of this place was a sheep farm owned by the Williamson-Balfour Company during the first half of the 20th century. Wikipedia claims that a king of this place was appointed to that position by the Bishop of Tahiti so that a colonizing power would have a leader to sign a treaty agreeing to their takeover this place. The mythical contest between the Hanau epe and Hanau momoko, or the \u201clong-ears\u201d and the \u201cshort-ears\u201d, may support the theory that this island was partially settled from the west. Representatives of elite residents of this island competed yearly to collect the first sooty (*) tern egg from a nearby island in what is now called the Birdman ritual. In addition to developing the rongorongo script, the people of this island set their most famous constructions on platforms called ahus. For 10 points, name this Pacific island owned by Chile and home of the moai statues.",
            "answer": "Rapa Nui (accept Easter Island or Isla de Pascua)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A subset of this group was subject to \u201cOperation Snatch\u201d, in which 200 of their children were taken from their families and forced to go to school. In 1907, these people lost about a third of their land to the government because they refused to have it titled under individual owners. The Sons of Freedom branch of this group organized numerous nude protests, believing that human skin was more perfect than clothes because it was made by God, and may have assassinated their own leader in a train bombing. That leader of this religious group was Peter Verigin, who led them for many years from exile in (*) Siberia, and it was Verigin who convinced this group to avoid alcohol and become nonviolent. Leo Tolstoy and Peter Kropotkin helped fund the emigration of 7400 people of this religious group to Canada. For 10 points, this is what sect of \u201cspirit wrestling\u201d Russian Christians?",
            "category": "History"
        }
    ],
    "bonuses": []
}